<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Cambium Regis: or, The office of His Maiesties Exchange Royall Declaring and iustifying his Maiesties right; and the conveniencie thereof. Published by authoritie.</title>
            <title>Cambium Regis.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1628</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 22 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A17734</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 4471</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117072</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99852287</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99852287</idno>
            <idno type="VID">17603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A17734)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 17603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1129:30)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Cambium Regis: or, The office of His Maiesties Exchange Royall Declaring and iustifying his Maiesties right; and the conveniencie thereof. Published by authoritie.</title>
                  <title>Cambium Regis.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 35, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by B. Alsop and T. Fawcet] for B. F[isher],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1628.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printers' and publisher's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Includes a petition to the king from the Goldsmiths.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Columbia University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Colm MacCrossan</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:17603:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17603:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>Cambium Regis:</hi> OR, THE OFFICE OF HIS MAIESTIES EXCHANGE ROYALL. Declaring and iuſtifying his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Right; and the Conveniencie thereof. <hi>Publiſhed by Authoritie.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>printer's device of Bernard Alsop, featuring a griffon seated on a stone or book, resting on a ball or globe with wings (McKerrow 339)</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>LONDON. Printed for <hi>B.F.</hi> 1628.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:17603:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:17603:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>Ntending to ſet downe in a ſummary way, the grounds of <hi>the Office of Exchange,</hi> and the cauſes of the late <hi>revi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving</hi> the <hi>execution</hi> thereof. I found it would be neceſſary by way of preface to levell and prepare the mindes of ſuch who perhaps haue bin attempted to be <hi>prepoſſeſſed</hi> with many vntrue and ſcandalous rumors touching the ſame, ſince in a thing although not <hi>new,</hi> yet by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon of diſvſage to ſome ſeeming <hi>as new,</hi> it may prevaile much in prejudice of a cauſe, that men haue falſe ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions or conceipts of that which is pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded or done; to the end therefore that the mind freed of theſe, may be placed in that even and cleere aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect as may be fit, for the right vnderſtanding and judging of what ſhall bee repreſented vnto it, I muſt from ſuch as may pervſe this ſhort Treatiſe, deſire by way of poſtulation or requeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">§. 1.</note> that notwithſtanding what they may haue heard, they doe not conceiue, that the <hi>Office,</hi> or graunt
<pb facs="tcp:17603:3"/>thereof in the Letters Patents intends or actually <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtraines</hi> the <hi>libertie of the ſubiect</hi> in <hi>generall,</hi> but that he is <hi>free,</hi> (as before the Patent.)</p>
            <p n="1">1. To ſell his plate veſſell, or other manufactures, or other gold or ſiluer whatſoeuer, to any Goldſmith, or other perſon whomſoeuer to his beſt advantage.</p>
            <p n="2">2 That he is <hi>free</hi> to carry his gold and ſilver immedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>atly to the mint there to haue the ſame coyned, whether he be a <hi>Merchant</hi> that imports the ſame from beyond the feas: Or <hi>other ſubiect,</hi> hauing the ſame from his Mines, of his Plate, receipts or monyes comming of his wares, or other commodities.</p>
            <p>Nor doth it <hi>reſtraine the Goldſmith, or other Tradeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man in particular.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. They may vſe their trade of <hi>Goldſmithrey,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Trades as fully and amply as heretofore they law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully might or could doe.</p>
            <p n="2">2. They may vſe and enioy, all ſuch <hi>franchiſes</hi> and other <hi>liberties</hi> and <hi>graunts</hi> which they lawfully haue or hold from the Charters of his Maieſtie or any his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deceſſors.</p>
            <p n="3">3. They may <hi>buy</hi> and <hi>Plate veſſell, burnt ſilver, broken ſilver or other</hi> in faſhion or out of faſhion, or any other <hi>manufacture</hi> to be imployed in their Trades or reſold, as they might doe before the Patent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. They may buy any <hi>gold or ſilver whatſoeuer</hi> or of <hi>whomſoeuer</hi> to make plate of, or to be vſed in the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all manufactures of their trades.</p>
            <p>Secondly,<note place="margin">§. 2.</note> I ſhould deſire, no man ſhould conceiue of this <hi>as grounded vpon the abſolute power and preroga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue royall of the King,</hi> But as the <hi>premption of Bullion,</hi> or Materials of mintage, is a right inherent and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>truſted
<pb facs="tcp:17603:3"/>truſted to the Crowne; ſo alwaies haue the <hi>Kings</hi> of this Realme exerciſed this office by their Farmers and Patentees as belonging to them <hi>by right and prerogatiue legall, A Right</hi> of ſuch nature, as that by which <hi>Royall mynes, Treaſure troue,</hi> and ſuch like doe belong vnto the <hi>Crowne,</hi> And as it is not raiſed, ſo is it not intended to be enlarged, or extended beyond the bounds and limitts ſet to it by the Law: or vpheld by any other means, then the ordinarie courſes of Iuſtice, free to all in his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Courts of Iudicature, to which euery man juſtly grieued by the Patent, or the execution thereof, is left to obtaine his lawfull rights and amends.</p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> that the office may no way bee taken as to ſauour of Monopolie; this including a <hi>reſtraint</hi> of what was lawfull; and <hi>a ſetting of a price</hi> vpon a free merchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſe, at the pleaſure of private perſons to their owne gaine, in prejudice of the publike: But the office is and ought to be acquited of both theſe Challenges, and moſt juſtly: For although the <hi>mettals of gold and ſilver</hi> (as things many waies vſefull) haue bin and are the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Trade, yet when they are <hi>conſidered as Bullion, and as the materials of Coine with reference to the Mint:</hi> In this <hi>relation,</hi> they become the <hi>ſole preragatiue and right of Princes</hi> who haue power to enſtampe them with their Image and ſuperſcription, thereby giuing them <hi>curran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie</hi> amongſt their people, and appointing them <hi>publique meaſures for</hi> the valuing and gouerning the eſtates and contracts of their ſubiects, whereupon it hath neuer bin lawfull heere, nor (in any well gouerned <hi>forreine ſlate</hi>) was there euer permitted <hi>a promiſcuous buying of Bullion,</hi> to buy, ſell or traffique gold or ſilver <hi>merchantwiſe, or to driue any Trade vpon the profit thereof,</hi> and ſo to come
<pb facs="tcp:17603:4"/>betwixt the Merchant, or other iubject, and the Mint, but to ſuch as were authoriſed and appointed by the State herevnto: <hi>This being the full proper and adaquate ſubiect of the Office of Exchange,</hi> The ſoueraignty of the Prince and State, hauing beene euer eſteemed faint and vaine <hi>in the forme and valuation of monyes;</hi> if the <hi>materials,</hi> and the ſupply thereof ſhould bee <hi>at the pleaſure of others;</hi> As heere it hath lately beene at the pleaſure of ſome few Goldſmiths, and <hi>accidentally</hi> brought to the Mint, when no offer of gaine did with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drawe their ſupplie. <hi>And for the price;</hi> that is alwaies <hi>cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine,</hi> though dependent vpon the Prince his ſtandard <hi>Bullion</hi> not like other merchandiſe, according to more or few buyers, plentie or ſcarcity, or the vſe or diſuſe thereof, or other accidents <hi>riſing or falling in price;</hi> but alwaies hauing one <hi>certaine and vnchoengeable value and rate: according to</hi> the weight <hi>and fineneſſe thereof,</hi> viz. <hi>That for gold and ſilver Bullion in forreine ſpecies or other, there be giuen a like, and the ſame quantity of gold or ſilver Corned equiualent weight for weight.</hi> The <hi>ſeller onely aba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the Coinage and price of Exchange,</hi> Both which are to be <hi>taxed</hi> by the <hi>authoritie of the</hi> Prince, <hi>or lawes</hi> of the State, as in this particular they are by his <hi>Maieſties In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dentures of the Mint:</hi> And <hi>of the Exchange,</hi> And the laſt being likewiſe according to Act of Parliament there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of made with much temper thereunto.<note place="margin">ix. H. v. c.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">§. 4.</note> 
               <hi>Nor</hi> will any I hope be much prejudiced with the murmures and complaints of ſome few <hi>exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging Goldſmiths,</hi> whoſe <hi>vſurped and abuſed Trade</hi> is here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by cut off, ſince (the premiſes conſidered) this will appeare to all to be but the <hi>power and practiſe</hi> of thoſe few (not many more then ten perſons) and their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailement
<pb facs="tcp:17603:4"/>with the reſt of the company, vpon falſe ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſtions of prejudices, neither granted nor claimed; Becauſe it wilbe impoſſible <hi>to aſſigne,</hi> or ſhew, how or wherein the <hi>true Goldſmith</hi> receiues prejudice, when he is not barred from buying, ſelling, or doing any thing that euer did or doth belong to their trades, or euer was vſed or practiſed but by thoſe few, who <hi>leauing off their proper trade of Goldſmithrie,</hi> and <hi>contrary to their Charter,</hi> are vnduely become <hi>Exchangers,</hi> Interlopers betwixt the Merchant and the Mint, And <hi>Intruders</hi> hereby vpon his Maieſties <hi>Regalities,</hi> to the loſſe of his Maieſtie in the profit of his Coynage, and Exchange; And generall prejudice of the Realme, <hi>by the opportunity they</hi> haue had and practiſed from hence, of being <hi>the ſole inſtruments of exportation</hi> of gold and ſilver to the ſtrangers, <hi>The ſorters and cullors</hi> out of all the weighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of his Maieſties coine, which they haue <hi>tranſported or moulten downe,</hi> occaſioning hereby the great <hi>ſcarcity of ſilver</hi> monyes, and the <hi>ſtanding ſtill of the Mint</hi> for ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver monyes euer ſince xj<hi rend="sup">mo</hi> of the late King, and by both a <hi>decreaſe of the</hi> trade and imployment of the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, And by all <hi>an impoueriſhment</hi> and deſtruction of the Realme.</p>
            <p>And now preſuming the indifferent and vnpartiall will (at leaſt) withhold his cenſures, vntill euery alle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation againſt the office ſhall be vpon particular exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination, cleered and <hi>reſolued;</hi> I deſiring, their like pati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of perufall, proceed to make manifeſt.</p>
            <p>Firſt, <hi>His Maieſties legall right thereunto.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>cauſes of his Maieſties, now reſuming the
<pb facs="tcp:17603:5"/>ſame and therein the conuenience thereof,</hi> and then to touch <hi>the forme of proceeding and debatements had in bringing the ſame to reſolution,</hi> from all which, <hi>ſatisfaction</hi> is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſented, vpon what <hi>iuſt, weighty, and conſiderable reaſons</hi> his Maieſtie hath <hi>reſtored</hi> to his Crowne, and <hi>reſumed</hi> CAMBIVM REGIS, or his Office of <hi>Exchange Royall.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="1" facs="tcp:17603:5"/>
               <head>Cambium Regis.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He right and Prerogatiue of <hi>Exchange</hi> of <hi>Bullion,</hi> hath alwaies beene a flower of the Crowne, and part of his Maieſties anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Reuenue, A maine part of Regalty, and mark of Soueraignty, For the power of Mintage or Coynage, being as it were but <hi>nomen mane,</hi> an emptie and vaine title when the Materials as <hi>Bullion</hi> was miniſtred and brought thether onely at the curteſie of others. The Kings of this Realme haue therefore alwaies enioyed, and continued this prero<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatiue of <hi>Exchange,</hi> as from the vtmoſt Extancie of <hi>Record,</hi> may appeare.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the firſt therefore made a Law, <hi>Quod nullus ſit auſus cambire denarios niſi Monetarius Regis,</hi> conioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning in one perſon both the offices of <hi>Exchanger:</hi> and Maſter worker of his Moneys, which the excellent Kings ſucceeding preſerued, as a flower of the Crowne, though in diſtinct and deuided Offices, vntill that about the beginning of <hi>Henry</hi> the 6. they came againe to bee conioyned.</p>
               <p>In the raigne of <hi>Richard</hi> the firſt, <hi>Guido de Voe.</hi> had and exerciſed the office of Exchange.</p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:17603:6"/>
               <p>King <hi>Iohn</hi> in <hi>Anno primo,</hi> for the conſideration of 1700<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitted to <hi>Hugo Cycell, Cambium totius Angliae:</hi> And in <hi>Anno</hi> 6. <hi>per Communem Conſilium,</hi> Ordinances being made an expreſſe Article was prohibiting all o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to make any exchange of money or ſiluer, but at the Kings <hi>Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the third in the Sixt yeare of his Raigne wrote to the <hi>Seabins</hi> and men of <hi>Ipree,</hi> That he <hi>Aſſenſu Conſilij</hi> had made proclamation, That no Engliſh man or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould make Exchange but onely at his Exchange at <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Canterbury.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>According whereunto for the ſum of 5000. Marks, he farmed out his Exchange; <hi>Anno</hi> 6. to <hi>Andrew Buc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kerill, Anno</hi> 9. to <hi>Euerard, Anno</hi> 35. to <hi>Bartholmew Caſtilion.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The place where the Kings Exchange was kept at this time, was by <hi>Paules,</hi> and gaue name to the ſtreet called the <hi>Old change,</hi> but in euidence the <hi>Old Exchange.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the firſt had his Exchanger with Prohibition that none elſe ſhould vſe it, <hi>Gregory Rock</hi> had it <hi>anno</hi> 8. And for eaſe of Merchants that imported Bullion, he cauſed tables of Exchanges to be ſet vp at ſeueral places.</p>
               <p>The Goldſmiths Charter; <hi>Anno</hi> 1. <hi>Edw:</hi> the firſt, makes mention that the Goldſmiths then by their peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion declared; <hi>That</hi> whereas heretofore no Merchant Engliſh or Stranger hath vſed to bring into this Land no manner of money forged, but onely Plate of Silver to make Esxchange with our <hi>Coyne.</hi> By which of the Goldſmiths owing ſhewing appeares. 1. That all im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported Silver (which then of right was onely Plate of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:17603:6"/>Silver) was to be carried to the Kings Exchange; And neither the Goldſmiths nor the Goldſmithrie heere is mentioned for Silver imported. Secondly, it is to bee obſerned; That the Exchange was to be made with his Maieſties Coyne, <hi>viz.</hi> by giving currant Coyne pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently for it.</p>
               <p>When divers Goldſmiths about 7. <hi>Edw:</hi> the ſecond, intruded vpon the Kings Officers, and would buy Gold and Siluer for the Mint, A Proclamation was made to the Contrarie, Commanding all ſellers to goe <hi>ad Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bium Regis.</hi> In his time, <hi>anno</hi> 5. <hi>William Hanſteed</hi> was Echanger, and <hi>anno</hi> 18. <hi>Roger de Frowick.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The like Prohibition was <hi>aſſenſu Conſilij</hi> by Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation vpon paine of impriſonment and forfeiture of all <hi>Anno</hi> xxv. Ed. the third, vpon like preiudice offered to the Kings profit then, hauing farmed out his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes, as <hi>Anno</hi> xxviij. to <hi>wickingham: Anno</hi> 35. to <hi>Guidon: Anno</hi> 40. to S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iue.</hi> And Tables of Exchanges were erected at <hi>Douer, Canterbury</hi> and other Ports of the Kingdome.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Rex per Aſſenſum Conſilij ſui Ordinanvit Quod Excam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biam Monetae ſuae tam auri quam argenti penes ipſum rema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neant vnde proclamari fecit quod nullus Ex cambium aut venditione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> monetaefaciat clam vel palam niſi per ipſum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gem ad illum Deputatu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſub paena impriſonamenti &amp; Amiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionis Monetae predictae. Claus de Anno xxv.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Quod nullus Commune Cambium teneat, nec aliquod pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficuum de eodem percipiat ſub paena faris facturae, monetae ſic Cambiata Excepto Cambiataere Regis iuxta formam Statuti Anno xxv. Ed:</hi> 3. <hi>Claus de An xxix. indorſo. vid. ſimiliter.</hi> Statutes of money made at York. ix. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Cap.</hi> 2. <hi>Item,</hi> that no falſe money bee brought into our Realme or
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:17603:7"/>elſewhere within our power vpon paine of forfeiture of ſuch money, Prouided alwayes, That all manner of people of what Realme or Dominion they bee of, may ſafely bring to the <hi>Exchange</hi> and to no place elſe, <hi>Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Siluer in plate, veſſell of Siluer, and all manner money of ſiluer,</hi> of what value ſoeuer it be, ſo that it be no falſe mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney and ſterling counterfeit, and there they ſhall receive good and conuenient Exchange.</p>
               <p>Cap. 7. <hi>Item</hi> That the Tables of Exchange, ſhalbe at <hi>Dover,</hi> and in other places, where and when it ſhall pleaſe vs, and your Counſell to make Exchanges; And that the Wardens of ſuch Tables, ſhall make ſuch Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changes, by the Teſtimony of Controuler, which wee ſhall put to them.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Money,</hi> Plate, or veſſell, intended or purpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to bee exported, or Counterfeit ſterling imported, being to be by that State, forfeited, The forfeitures were to be deliuered to the Exchanges by Indenture whereby the Wardens may be charged. <hi>Cap</hi> 9.</p>
               <p>Exchanges ſhalbe ordained in good Townes, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as ſhall ſeeme beſt to our ſoveraigne Lord the King, for the profit of him and his people. And that it ſhalbe ordained in certaintie, what ſhalbe giuen in Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change for euery peece of gold. xviij. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. It ſhall be lawfull for euery man to Exchange gold for ſiluer, or ſiluer for gold, or for gold and ſiluer gold, ſo that no man hold no Exchange, nor take no profit, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king ſuch Exchange vpon payne of forfeiture of the money ſo exchanged; Except the Kings Exchanger, who takes profit, according to the Ordinance before made. <hi>Anno</hi> 25. <hi>Cap.</hi> 12.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17603:7"/>
               <p>All Merchants priuie and Strangers, may ſafely bring within your ſaid Realme and lands. <hi>Plate of ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, and Billets of gold,</hi> And all other manner of gold, or all money of Gold or ſilver to our Bullion or to our Exchanges which wee ſhall doe ordaine at our Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples and elſewhere. Taking there money of our Coyne of gold or ſiluer Couenable to the value, xxvij. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. Cap. 14.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard</hi> the III. continued the farme of Bullion as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth by his graunt to<note n="a" place="margin">Roc. Fin. an 11. <hi>Ric.</hi> 2.</note> 
                  <hi>Salisbury</hi> and others; with Proclamation vpon paine of forfeiture, that none elſe ſhould vſe it.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the IIII. granted out the Office of Exchange, <hi>anno</hi> 1. And <hi>anno</hi> ix. prohibited all other but his owne Exchanger.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Henry</hi> the V<hi rend="sup">th</hi> graunted out this Office, <hi>anno</hi> 11. to<note n="a" place="margin">Ret. Pat. de anno 2. pars a mem. 34.</note> 
                  <hi>Lodowick Iohn;</hi> with Prohibition of all<note n="b" place="margin">Patent. de anno 2. pars 2. m. 23. Et om. 5. m. 1.</note> others: And by Indenture, <hi>anno</hi> ix. Conſtituted<note n="c" place="margin">Clauſ. de an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>no ix. Dorſ. m. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>Iohn Pateſley</hi> Citizen and Goldſmith his Exchanger with ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Covenants; And for the Out-Ports, and other parts of the Realme from <hi>London;</hi> There was <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſu directa iuſticiarijs de Aſsiſa per Totam Angli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17603:8"/>ad Communìcandum &amp; tractandum cum quibus Cur que legijs qui officium Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bij Mometae Regis habere &amp; occupare voluerit. Patent. de anno</hi> 19. <hi>part.</hi> 2. <hi>mem.</hi> 8.</p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:17603:7"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Statut.</hi> ix. <hi>H. v. c.</hi> 2.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The King ſhall doe to bee or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dayned his</hi> Exchanges <hi>of Gold and Silver in the Citie of Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don and elſewhere, in the Realms for the eaſe of his peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, Which ſhall bee holden in open places in high Streets; And that all they which will come to the Tower of London, there to haue money new Coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, they ſhall haue money of new Coyne, and thereof ſhall bee deliuered within Eight dayes according to the true va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue paying the Coynage. And that they which will not goc to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:17603:8"/>the Tower but thereof bee deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered at the</hi> Exchanges, <hi>ſhall pay for the Exchange after the rate of Penny for the Noble, with the</hi> Seignorage <hi>and</hi> Coy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage.</p>
               <p>Cap. 4. <hi>Item,</hi> That they which ſhall bee <hi>wardens, Surveyors,</hi> and miniſters of <hi>Exchanges</hi> out of the Tower, ſhall bee holden and bounden to bring all their Gold and Silver, which they ſhall receiue by way of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, or Buy, by colour of their Office vnto the Tow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, there to be moulten and made into Coyne, in aug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentation &amp; increaſe of the money for the profit of the Realme and eaſe of the people, without being ſould, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liened, or put to any other vſe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Bartholmew Goldbeater</hi> was Exchanger by Indenture at the time of the Demiſe of <hi>Hen.</hi> 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi>, who<note n="a" place="margin">Rot. Parl. an. H. vj noſtr. 35.</note> was com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maunded notwithſtanding the voydance of his Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, by the Kings death to continue the Exerciſe of that office (as the Record ſaith) <hi>to the Profit of the King and people;</hi> and vpon ſupplication of allowance for waſte, was allowed for Exchange <hi>Penie halfe-penie</hi> per Noble. After whoſe death the ſaid Office by Letters Patents and Indenture, was grannted vnto<note n="b" place="margin">Patent. ann. x. pars 1. mem. 29.</note> 
                  <hi>William Ruſſe</hi> Citizen and Ieweller, to haue <hi>Iuxta forma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; effe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctum Indenturaru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Anno xxiiij.<note n="c" place="margin">Dorſ. Clauſ. de. cod. anno memb. 30.</note> 
                  <hi>Robert Mansfield</hi> was made Exchanger by Letters Patents and Indenture. Anno xxvij.<note n="d" place="margin">
                     <p>Clauſ. de codem 23. in. dorſ.</p>
                     <p>Vid.: ſtat. 1. H. vj cap. 1. &amp; 2. H. vj. cap. 10.</p>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>Richard Tunſtall.</hi> In all which Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, the Covenants are gr<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>onnded vpon, and purſue
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:17603:8"/>the Proviſions of the Acts aboue mentioned of <hi>anno</hi> ix. <hi>Hen.</hi> v. <hi>Capit.</hi> 2. &amp; 4.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Edward</hi> the IIII. in the viij.<hi rend="sup">th</hi> of his Raigne, did ordayne<note n="a" place="margin">Patent. de eod. an. pars. 3. m. 2.</note> 
                  <hi>William</hi> Lord <hi>Haſtings,</hi> Maſter and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of his money, &amp;c. <hi>And Keeper of all manner of Changes and Outchanges in the Tower of London, Realme of England, towne of Callis and marches of the ſame,</hi> to haue to himſelfe and De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puties according to his let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents and Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. In <hi>anno</hi> xxij.<note n="b" place="margin">Pat. de eod. an. pars. 3. m. 8.</note> 
                  <hi>Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholmew Read</hi> Citizen and Goldſmith of London, had the ſame office by let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents and Inden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Richard</hi> the III. granted this Office to <hi>Iohn Kendall</hi> his Secretary, with Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, <hi>anno</hi> 1.</p>
               <p>And thus all the reigne of <hi>Hen.</hi> the vij.<note n="*" place="margin">Man. Cotten.</note> it was conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nued, and ſo along vntill
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:17603:9"/>the looſe times of <hi>Henry</hi> the viij. vpon occaſion of his baſe moneys (whereupon no conſtant Exchanges could be made) made way to the Enchrochment of the Goldſmiths <hi>who</hi> (as the right worthy Sir <hi>Robert Cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton</hi> hath obſerued) <hi>hauing of late in our times caſt off their proper Trade of Gould<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmithery, are become vnduly to the Kings preiudice the Maſters and Commanders hereby of the Kings Mint. And ſo by ſetting themſelues in the ſoueraignes dignitie, bring the King to be waged and ſet on worke by his owne ſubiects, Contrary to the vſe of the former beſt times in this ſtate. And to the practiſe of the wiſeſt and grea teſt Princes in forreine parts.</hi> The Exchange of Coine or emption of Bullion being almoſt in all neighboring ſtates <hi>Officium publicum,</hi> And in the power and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of Princes none be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing at liberty to exerciſe
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:17603:9"/>
                  <hi>leſtat. de Changeiur,</hi> but by facultie from the Prince, And with Relation to his Mynts.</p>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:17603:8"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Statut.</hi> 4. <hi>Hen.</hi> vij. <hi>cap.</hi> 5.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>No fine ſiluer to be allayed or ſold to any but to officers of</hi> Mints, Changes, or Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths, <hi>for</hi> augmentation <hi>and</hi> amending of Coine or Plate: <hi>&amp;c. But not to ſell to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon Siluer allayed. And that</hi> no Goldſmith <hi>ſell no fine ſiluer nor any ſiluer allayed to any per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon whatſoeuer, nor one Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith to another.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>By Proclamation</hi> 5. <hi>Ed.</hi> vj. <hi>this ſtatute of</hi> 3. <hi>Hen.</hi> vij. <hi>(which expreſly ratifies and confirmes the Act. of</hi> 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>orderned for Exchanges</hi> ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pra) <hi>is commanded to be put in Execution.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And in the Act of</hi> 18. <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz.</hi> 15. <hi>for reformation of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſes in Goldſmiths, her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Mints and Changes are nominated diſiunctiuely and by Proclamation of</hi> 43. <hi>Eliz. this Act of</hi> 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Concerning Exchanges is enioyned to bee duyly obſerued.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:17603:9"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note that this Act. of</hi> 25. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>made for Exchanges, is mentioned in the Indentures of the Kings, with their Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers: as an.</hi> 28. <hi>Ed.</hi> 3. <hi>Wicking<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham,</hi> ix. <hi>H.</hi> v. <hi>to Pateſly,</hi> x. <hi>Hen.</hi> 6. <hi>to Wilitam Ruſ.</hi> xxiiij. <hi>to Manſfield,</hi> xxxvj. <hi>to Ton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtall</hi> viij. <hi>Ed.</hi> 4. <hi>to M. L. Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtirgs,</hi> xxij. <hi>to Reed. In all which and in all other Juden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of this Office the King ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly couenants to Proclaime: That none other hold any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Exchange or take profit. This Stat. being alſo Proclai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> ix. <hi>H.</hi> v. <hi>mem.</hi> 6.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:17603:9"/>
               <p>By all which <hi>Acts of Parliament, Charters Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> cleered and interpreted by the <hi>Letters Patents, and Indentures,</hi> and the vninterrupted practiſe and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of that Office for many hundred of yeares, Is made moſt euident.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. That the Exchange or buying of Bullion belongs to his Maieſtie <hi>Iure ſucceſſionis,</hi> by right deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued from his Anceſtors Kings of England: as part of his ancient Right and Reuenue: And likewiſe <hi>Iure conceſsionis,</hi> by Grants and Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhments of ſeuerall Acts of Parliament.</item>
                  <item>2. That it is no part of the Goldſmiths trade to buy or exchange Bullion; or lawfull to any other to trade Gold or ſiluer Merchantwiſe, to make profit thereof, ſaue onely to his Maieſties Exchanger.</item>
                  <item>3. That the Exchange was deuided and ſeuered from the Mynt, or Bullion: And that diuers places of Exchange were both in London and elſewhere out of the Tower.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And to conclude the point of his Maieſties <hi>legall inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt</hi> in the Exchange of Bullion, the Charter of the Goldſmiths expreſſely both warrants his Maieſties Right, and ſhewes that they had no libertie to buy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>any Gold or Siluer, but with reference to be made and conuerted into Plate. As more particularly will
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:17603:10"/>be explained in Anſweare to ſome legall pointes of their petition made to the Lords of his Maieſties moſt Honorable Priuy Councell.</p>
               <p>By all which, though it doth euidently appeare, That the <hi>Exchange</hi> of Bullon neither euer was, nor now is, any part or branch of the goldſmiths trade; to which by his ſervice and freedome he is entituled. Neverthe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe it may not ſeeme altogether vnuſefull to Collect the ſame likewiſe from the points enſuing.</p>
               <p>That this is intimated in the very name of Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmithrie,<note place="margin">§. 1.</note> importing a manufactury or handy craft: they being <hi>Auri-fabri,</hi> not <hi>Auri-emptores,</hi> or <hi>Auri-ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditores.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That by the old Orders of the Companie of Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths.<note place="margin">§. 2.</note> It was required as a proofe of his skill and ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficiencie, That euery one before hee was made <hi>free</hi> was to make a peece of Plate or other worke called his <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter-peece,</hi> without which hee was refuſable: but it was neuer heard they were examined vpon their skill in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Coynes or ſeuerall goodneſſes of Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver.</p>
               <p>That within theſe 60.<note place="margin">§. 3.</note> yeares laſt paſt; The Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmith-row in <hi>Cheape</hi> or Goldſmithrie, was all inhabited by the working-Goldſmiths, euery Shop hauing his worke-houſes neceſſary for the ſeuerall vſe of their Trades.</p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:17603:10"/>
               <p>That the commonaltie or generalitie of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany,<note place="margin">§. 4.</note> doth neither pretend vnto, nor know what be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the skill or cunning of the Exchanges, nor are acquainted or practiſed in the values or fineneſſes of <hi>for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Species:</hi> And as within theſe 30. yeares laſt paſt there were few or none: So at this time there are not many more then tenne perſons who to any purpoſe are skilfull or traders in forreine Coynes.</p>
               <p>That it is lawfull, for any Book-binder,<note place="margin">§. 5.</note> Merchants man or other perſon whatſoeuer, being free of any other Company: To ſet vp as an <hi>Exchanging Goldſmith;</hi> which ſhewes that to bee no part of the Trade: And vpon ſome remonſtrances vnder the hands of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monaltie, it will bee made appeare, that they haue diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claymed this <hi>Exchanging miſtery</hi> eyther to bee part of the ir trade; or the <hi>Exchangers</hi> of right to haue any thing to doe in their Company.</p>
               <p>And laſtly,<note place="margin">§. 6.</note> if this Exchanging had been part of the Goldſmiths true and ancient Trade, it would haue bin vſed by them time out of minde as appertayning to their Trade; Whereas contrariwiſe it moſt evidently appeares, That many Goldſmiths in the Raignes of ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verall Kings did exerciſe this buſineſſe of Exchange, and buying and ſelling of Bullion, Not by reaſon of their trades, but by vertue of Letters Patents from the Kings of this Realme, and that without oppoſition or pretention of any other of their Company thereunto. Thus <hi>William Salisbury</hi> Goldſmith was Exchanger, 1.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:17603:11"/>
                  <hi>Ric.</hi> 1. <hi>Iohn Pateſley ix. Hen. v. William Ruſſe</hi> 2. <hi>Hen. vi. Bartholmew Read, xxij. Edw.</hi> the 4. and others. By all which is apparently ſhewed. <hi>The</hi> exchanging of gold and ſiluer to be no part of the Goldſmiths trade or to belong vnto them. And by conſequence that by the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice they are not reſtrained or debarred from any lawfull benefit or vſe of their Trades.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. 2. The Cauſes of his Maieſties now reſuming the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change of Bullion.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Beſides the more generall Cauſe moving his Maieſty to reſume the Exchange of Bullion, which was,</hi>
                  <note n="a" place="margin">
                     <p>Ad jura regni ne depereant ſeu per aliquorum vſurpationes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>debitas aliquatinus ſubſtrahantur quatenus iuſte poterimus manu te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendum ſubſtracta<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> &amp; occupata ſi quae ſuerint ad Statum debitum re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uocanda nec, non ad impugnatores eorundam iurium noſtrorum refrae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nandos, Et prout convenit juxta eorundam demerita puniendos co ſtudioſius nos decet operam adhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beri &amp; ſolicitius extendere manum noſtram quod ad hoc vinculo iura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menti teneri dignoſcimur &amp; aſtrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gi plureſque conſpicimus iurà illa pro viribus impugnare.</p>
                     <p>Regiſt brevium. Ad iura Regia. fol. 61.6.</p>
                  </note> to preſerue the rights of his Crowne and revenue, <hi>Some ſpeciall Motiues ſeeme to haue beene raiſed, from thoſe Abuſes and errors, which ſuch of the Goldſmiths as became Exchangers haeue practiſed, whereby they haue greatly exhauſted the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney of the Realme, and depraved and enfeebled the reſidue. And as the</hi> Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation <hi>not</hi> colourably <hi>but</hi> truely ſpeakes, <hi>Theſe Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> aue from hence growne vnto that <hi>licentiouſnes, That they haue for divers yeares preſumed for their priuate
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:17603:11"/>Lucar and gaine, and daily doe preſume to ſort and weigh all ſorts of moneyes currant within our Realme, to the end to Call out all the Old and new moneyes which eyther by not wearing or any other accident are weightier then the reſt, which weightieſt and beſt monyes haue not onely him</hi> molten downe, <hi>for the making of Plate veſſell and other manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures, but even</hi> Traded and ſould <hi>to</hi> Merchant ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers <hi>and others who haue</hi> tranſported <hi>the ſame, whereby the Conſumption of our Coynes hath bin greatly occaſioned. Not onely to</hi> the ſcarcitie <hi>of Currant moneyes, eſpecially of</hi> Siluer Coyne, <hi>but alſo to the great depravation and enfee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bling of the Remainder of our Silver moneyes not exported or conſumed by the abuſes and practiſes aforeſayd. And to the</hi> Raiſing <hi>of the Silver even of our owne Moneyes to a Rate and price aboue our Mynt, and aboue what they are truely Currant for. By reaſon whereof no Silver can bee brought thither but to the loſſe of ſuch as bring the ſame, Contrary to the Lawes and Policie of our Realme, and of di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers acts of Parliament, and of late Proclamation in that caſe provided and publiſhed. The longer permiſsion of all which would not onely redound to the impeachment of our Prerogatiue Royall: but doth directly tend to the impove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhment and deſtruction of our Realmes.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now that the Exchanging Goldſmiths haue had by the Advantage of their <hi>Exchanging,</hi> the <hi>Opportunitie</hi> of being the maine Sorters and Cullers of the weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt moneyes, and haue ſold and moulten downe the ſame, is convinced;</p>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:17603:12"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1. From the Conviction of the Merchant-Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers and others in the <hi>Scar-chamber;</hi> The Exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination of the Gold ſmiths, and their Bookes being the maine proofe againſt them: Since all or the greateſt part they exported, was bought of the Exchanging Goldſmith.</item>
                  <item>2 That his Maieſtie found this vpon Examination, as is Expreſſed and declared in the Proclama<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of ix. King IAMES made againſt Melting or Conveying out of the Kings Dominions of Gold or Silver coyned or currant in the ſame.</item>
                  <item>3 That it is notorionſly knowne that it hath for this 30. yeares and opwards bin the vſuall courſe of Exchanging Goldſmiths, to make their prentiſes and ſeruants, euery morning to runne from ſhop to ſhop, to enquire after and buy vp all weighty and heauy Gold at any ouer price, all which they haue ſold to <hi>Dutchmen</hi> &amp; others to be tranſported to their Mints: And euer ſince the Proclamation of the xj. of the ſaid King (which enhanſed the gold, whereby the profit was turned vpon the ſiluer.) They haue practiſed and ſtill doe practiſe to cull and ſort out all weighty and heauy moneys which they haue ſold for furniſhing the Mynts of <hi>Holland,</hi> and of the Eaſt-countries: witneſſe the pieces of Thirteene-pence halfepenies, Old ſhillings of <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Nine-pence and foure<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:17603:12"/>halfepeny <hi>pieces</hi> being weighty monies, whereof none are now to be met withall.</item>
                  <item>4. That hereby they haue raiſed the price of ſiluer by degrees, to 2.<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>per</hi> ounce aboue the value of the Mint, the immediate conſequence whereof hath bin the ſtanding ſtill of the Mint for ſiluer Moneyes euer ſince the xj. of King <hi>Iames,</hi> to the great ſcarcity of ſiluer Monies; the decreaſe of trade and imployment of the ſubiect both which are moued by plentie of money.</item>
                  <item>5. That it is notoriouſly knowne, that ſiluer weighty moneys are by certaine perſons that run vp, &amp; downe to ſhopkeepers and others, vnder pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Exchanging gold gathered and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together; And ſold by the Ounce to bee moulten downe to make plate off.</item>
               </list>
               <p>All which praemiſes conſidered, It is a thing of no great maruaile though <hi>Melchior wink</hi> late Mynt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maſter of Amſterdam, amongſt many other of his ſervices to that ſtate gaue in a memoriall of his gai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning them, LX. M.<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. <hi>per annum,</hi> by melting downe <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Coine</hi> which gaine Argues an immenſe ſumme to haue bin moulten downe.</p>
               <p>For reſtitution of which Right to the Crowne, and to reforme and ſtop the further continuance of theſe and ſuch like abuſes, tending to the dimunition and depra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of Engliſh Coyne, and procuring the ſcarcitie of
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:17603:13"/>money eſpecially of Silver hath his Maieſty beene plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to Reſume and Re-eſtabliſh, the Office of his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change Royall.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 3.</hi> Of the Conveniences of the Office of Exchange.</head>
               <p>The Policie and Lawes of this Realme, haue alwaies aymed at and intended <hi>The increaſe</hi> and augmentation of Money; moſt eſpecially that of Silver: And this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers wayes.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Firſt, by procuring the Importation of Bullion, and to this end haue enforced the Exporter of Staple Commodities, to returne ſome proportio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall part of Bullion; as 14. <hi>Edw.</hi> 3. cap. 21. <hi>Two markes</hi> ſilver for euery Sacke of Wooll: or that Wooll, woolfels and Tynne ſhould bee ſould for ready money. Euery <hi>Sarpler</hi> of Wooll of the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue of 12. Markes, to make good to the Mynt ſixe pound of Bullion.</item>
                  <item>2. Secondly, by preſeruing it aſwell in i'ts kinde by prouiding againſt Exportation<note n="a" place="margin">20. Ed. 1.9. Ed. 3.2. H. 6. Proct. 9. Iac. o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</note> and the mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting it downe to make Plate or other Manufa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctures of<note n="b" place="margin">9 Ed. 3. ca. 3.17. R. 2. ca. 2.17. Ed. 4. ca. 1.</note>: And if any monies thorough time or or other practiſe, became vncurrant, then the ſame to be converted into Money againe, and not bee diverted from Coyne.<note n="c" place="margin">
                        <hi>Ed. 1.</hi> Statut. de moneta por<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum Raſtall titul. money <hi>2.</hi>
                     </note>.</item>
                  <item>3. Laſtly, by providing,<note n="d" place="margin">2. H. 6. ca. 13. 18. Eliz. cap. 15.5. Ed. 6. <hi>Tit. Exchange Raſtall</hi> 25. Ed. 3. Procl. 43. E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liz. 10. Iac. 61. &amp; 16.</note> That none ſhould giue a price for Bullion aboue the Rate of the Mynt:
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:17603:13"/>For it is not to be expected that any Bullion either of Gold or ſilver ſhal euer be brought to the Mint, when the Owner may haue a greater price, then at the Mynt, eyther to be tranſported, or to be Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verted to make Plate or other things of. This a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeing likewiſe with the Policie of <hi>Spaine,</hi> which though it bee the Spring and fountaine from whence the greateſt ſtreames of filuer haue beene derived into other parts, yet an ounce of ſilver there will alwaies yeeld the ſeller ſix pence or one <hi>Reall</hi> more at the Mint, then to be ſold to any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for any purpoſe whatſoeuer, concurring likewiſe with the practiſe of other States.</item>
               </list>
               <p>
                  <hi>Plentie of Money</hi> being then the <hi>Marke</hi> or <hi>Ayme</hi> by approachment wherevnto, or declination from whence the conveniencie or inconueniencie of the office of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change muſt be judged. And theſe the ſubordinate meanes to obtaine the ſame, directed and leuelled to that end by diuers acts of Parliament. The next En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quirie is, whether theſe ends may not more probably beattained by the due exerciſe of the Office, Then by ſtill permitting the promiſcuous buying and felling of <hi>Bullion,</hi> and a common Trade and Traſſiquing in it, And this by way of compariſon.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. The Goldſmiths haue beene found to be the ſole in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments of Exportation, and a moſt neceſſarie and effectuall meanes thereunto, without whoſe mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtery the weightieſt or beſt moneys, or <hi>Bullion</hi> of gold and ſiluer could not bee got together<note n="b" place="margin">Procla. <hi>r.</hi> feb. <hi>16.</hi> Iac.</note> to fit the opportunity of tranſportation, But theſe Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changing
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:17603:14"/>Goldſmiths being taken away, the tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porters cannot be fitted, or their turnes ſerued, and ſo the tranſportation will decreaſe: But the Office of his Maieſties Exchange, is to aſſemble and ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther together the <hi>materials</hi> of Myntage, &amp; the ſame to deliuer to the Mynt, there to bee coyned for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of money, and this by the teſtimony<note n="c" place="margin">9. Ed. 3. c. 7. &amp; 9. H. 5. c. 2.</note> of a Controuler of the Exchange appointed thereunto by his Mareſtie.</item>
                  <item>2. The Goldſmiths culls and ſorts likewiſe out, the weighty Monies from time to time, and melts them downe, or ſels them to bee moulten downe to be conuerted to Plate, and for diuers other vſes. The <hi>Exchanger</hi> neither Culls nor ſorts, nor will permit any ſuch culling or ſorting, but will haue an eye hereunto, as well becauſe it occaſions the overpri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Silver: as alſo becauſe they hereby continue an vnlawfull trading of Coyne to his preiudice.</item>
                  <item>3. The Goldſmith hath hereby occaſioned the price of ſiluer to riſe by degrees to 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                     <hi>per ounce</hi> aboue the value of the Mynt: The effect whereof hath beene the ſtanding ſtill of the Mynt: And the raiſing of the price of Plate from time to time; And the cul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and melting downe of his Maieſties Coine, But the <hi>Exchanger</hi> neither can nor will doe any of theſe, And all theſe abuſes, proceeding onely from the <hi>Exchanging Goldſmiths</hi> will ceaſe, when their v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurped Trade ſhall be taken from them, and they no longer permitted their Exchanging without which they wil not be accommodated for theſe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:17603:14"/>
               <p>Now though the auoydance of theſe pernitious courſes, tending to the impoueriſhment and deſtruction of the Realme, be a good and conueniencie ſufficient to perſwade and maintaine the reſumption of this ſtart-vp trade, and the vſefulnes of the Office: Yet the due ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution of the office, and the parts incident therevnto will be further beneficiall to the Realme.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin" type="runSum">1. Importation advanced.</note> By publike Tables to be ſet vpp by the Exchanger wil be made knowne, the right valuation of For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reine Coynes to ours. And this will direct the mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chant to ſell our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>modities to the juſt price, which will advance the ſtocke of the Kingdome, and cauſe importation of Coyne and <hi>Bullion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. By the true and certaine value and tate ſet vppon all forreine Coines and <hi>Bullion,</hi> the Merchant will driue a more certaine trade then heretofore; For being ſure to receiue his ready mony for his <hi>Bullion</hi> at his returne, and being before informed of the true rates, this cannot. likewiſe but incourage and aduance the Importation.</item>
                  <item>3. The traueller inwards, or whoſoeuer is owner of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny forreine Coines in any the out part or place of landing, hauing occaſion of currant moneys, muſt take the pleaſure of the buyer to his exceeding great loſſe, for particuler men will not deale with vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne Coynes but vpon certainty of exceeding gaine; But the <hi>deputies</hi> here muſt gine the full va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lue, which will likewiſe further the Importation.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:17603:15"/>
               <list>
                  <item>1.<note place="margin" type="runSum">3. Exportation hindered.</note> The Exchanging <hi>Goldſmith</hi> being put by, by the Execution of this Office, the inſtruments and meanes of Exportation being cutt off, The Export it ſelfe will ceaſe, or be much diminiſhed.</item>
                  <item>2. Moneyes promiſcuouſly currant are not Expor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table, but the weighty and culled moneyes: But the Exchanging Goldſmith, the Culler and Sor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of theſe being cut off. The Export will like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe thus be diminiſhed.</item>
                  <item>3. The Exchanger and his Deputies in all the Ports will haue an eye to the execution of the Lawes and Ordinances againſt Exportation, whoſe better ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecution will much prevent carrying out of <hi>Bullion.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4. Forreyne Coynes in the out Ports and heere, are kept and preſerued to ſerue the occaſion of the Travailer, or Merchant outwards, but bought by the Exchanger, are forthwith cutt in peices. And cannot bee exported but are Conuerted into his Maieſties Coynes.</item>
                  <item>5. Lightned and vncurrant Coynes of Gold bought by the Goldſmith, are eyther ſold to be tranſported or moulten downe, being the beſt moneyes for theſe purpoſes: <hi>(As thoſe wherein the Coynage is ſaued)</hi> But ſold to the Exchanger, are in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of the ſeller cut in pieces, And re-conuerted into Coyne, whereby the ſtocke of money doth not decreaſe.</item>
               </list>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:17603:15"/>
               <p>The Advancement of his Maieſties profit in the Mynt is a conſequent to all:<note place="margin" type="runSum">2. Aduance his Maieſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties profit in the Mint.</note> For all Bullion comming to the Exchanges, is by Covenant and <hi>Compulſarily</hi> carried to the Exchanges; and this by the teſtimony of a <hi>Controuler</hi> appointed to overſee the ſame, and to Charge the Exchanger with the <hi>Bullion</hi> bought by him, and muſt not bee ſold or aliened to any other vſe; Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe his Maieſtie or the State ſhall thinke fit to licenſe ſome determinate quantitie to be ſold vpon promiſe to prouide the like quantitie againe from the parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond the Seas, vpon the immediate contract of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changer for the ſame. In which caſe the Money of the Realme is not diminiſhed. But the Goldſmiths carry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Bullion</hi> to the Mynt is but <hi>accidentall</hi> and at their pleaſures, and onely then when the price of the Mynt exceeds the rate of any other for the ſame. This was the reaſon why before Gold was enhanſed 9. <hi>Iacob.</hi> they ſel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome or neuer carried any to the Mynt, the Merchant giuing them a greater price for the ſame. And euer ſince that time, the profit falling vpon Silver, They haue not carried into the Mynt any conſiderable quantitie of Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, by which the Mynt hath not only ſtood ſtill for ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer monyes, but by this and the exportation and mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting downe the Silver monyes, there is ſcarce ſiluer e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough ſeft to driue the Trade of the Countrey, to the great hinderance and decay of Trade, to the leſſening the imployment and ſetting on worke of the Subiect. To omit that the remnant of the money of Silver are ſo by lightning depraued. That theſe which Run in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſcuous payments wants neare ix.<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. tayle <hi>per centum</hi> of their juſt weight.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:17603:16"/>
               <p>Beſides theſe, wee may herein further conſider, That it is a point of <hi>Honour</hi> and <hi>Iuſtice</hi> in the State: <hi>That there ſhould be a certayne and invariable price ſet vpon Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion, forreyne or other vncurrant Coynes,</hi> whereby they may neither be ouerpriſed to the detriment of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-wealth, and all ſuch as haue occaſion to vſe any maniſacture made of them: As likewiſe, that the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect be ſeured, that neither his Ignorance nor neceſſity, ſhould betray him to Deceit; But that there ſhould bee ordayned ſer and fired to the Ignorant, as well as the skilfull, to him that is vrged by his occaſions, as well as to him that may forbeare; a <hi>loyall</hi> and <hi>legall</hi> price of Coyne or <hi>Bullion,</hi> which <hi>can bee</hi> aſcertayned no other way but by Re-erecting <hi>Cambium Regis.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But theſe Conſiderations will perhaps with ſome bee more prevalent, when they ſhall reciue full ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction in the cleere ſolution of thoſe Difficulties, which by the Goldſmiths and others, both before his Maieſtie and the Lords of the Priuie Counſell, and elſe-where haue beene obiected, and oppoſed to the ſayd Office, in charging the ſame with pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lique preiudices, <hi>Which were theſe:</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Artic.</hi> 1.<note place="margin">Petition Goldſmiths. <hi>Obiect.</hi>
                     </note> That the Office ſought to bee renewed, hath beene ſo long out of vſe. That the ſudden al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teration will bee a great hindering to the Trade and vent of Cloath, which if it proue ſo, will not eaſily bee reſtored though the Patent bee layd downe. And therefore without good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:17603:16"/>aſſurance of the Event inconuenient to be put in Execution.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Artic.</hi> 2. It will be a great meanes o hinder Impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of <hi>Bullion.</hi> And by conſequence will cauſe Exportation of Gold and Silver, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by both his Maieſtie will be much prejudiced in the profits of his Mynt, and trade and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merce much hindered.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Artic.</hi> 5. By the Indenture betwixt the Kings Maieſtie and the Earle, it is mentioned, that the <hi>Exchan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> ſhall take onely for the Exchange ſo much as ſhall be agreed betwixt him and the bringer in of <hi>Bullion.</hi> So that it be not aboue the rate of j<hi rend="sup">d</hi> for the <hi>Noble</hi> of Gold or ſiluer which is a great burrhen to the <hi>Importers,</hi> and will be loſſe to the people in euery ounce of gold x<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. which is in money in the pound weight of gold x s. And the like prejudice will enſue in ſiluer, whereas the Goldſmith doth ordinarily make his Exchange for 2. s. and leſſe in the pound weight.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Artic.</hi> 6. It will be dangerous to the liues and States of Merchants that import <hi>Bullion,</hi> to be enfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to bring it to one hand onelyl by which meanes their importation of <hi>Bullion</hi> of forreine Countries may be reuealed. It being in moſt kindomes Capitall or confiſcation of goods to Export <hi>Bullion.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:17603:17"/>
               <p>Theſe are the Obiect ons which haue bcene made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Office as publikely inconuenient aſwell by the Goldſmiths in their Petition to the Lords as others. To which though euery one from the Precedent decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions many make cleere anſwere: And that it ought to ſuffice that hauing bin ſolemnely debated before his Maieſtie, vpon a long and full hearing they haue beene reſolued: yet for the generall ſatisfaction, ſome part of what was anſwered to them may be repeated.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the firſt;</hi> That it was not imaginable how the Office could ſtop the vent of Cloth: Nor could bee aſſigned how or wherein this trade ſhould here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by be endangered. And his Maieſtie propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing to this obiection, it ſhould be declared in <hi>Indiuiduo</hi> how or wherein this hinderance ſhould be occafioned. Vpon <hi>Nihil dicit</hi> the obiection vaniſhed, and was diſcharged. And ſince experience hath taught that the ſame was but as a phanſie preſented to a muſe, ſuch as could be diſturbed by generalites and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>To the ſecond.</hi> That being onely generall, it fell off like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vpon the ſame reaſon, for want of their ſhewing how or which way the execution of the Office ſhould either hinder the Import, or aduance the export of <hi>Bullion,</hi> or decreaſe his Maieſties profit in the Mint, otherwiſe or in o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther manner then as this followed from the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuing Articles.</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:17603:17"/>
               <p>Wherefore to the 5. <hi>Art.</hi> Containing the burthen of the j<hi rend="sup">d</hi> in the <hi>Noble</hi> to the Importer whence (ſay they) he wil be diſcouraged, is anſwered diuers wayes.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The Importer being neither by the <hi>Letters Patents</hi> nor the Proclamation reſtrained but at liberty to goe eyther to the Mynt or to the Exchanges at his election, doth not pretend himſelfe grieued or at all diſcouraged And for the j<hi rend="sup">d</hi> in the <hi>Noble,</hi> ſo long as he receiues bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and accommodation by the Exchange, the price of the Exchange, is due of Iuſtice <hi>Qui ſentit commodum ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire debet &amp; onus:</hi> The benefits he receiues thereby are 1. The Importers occaſion in the vſe and imployment of ready money for paying of cuſtomes wages and other neceſſaries is ſerued: 2. Hee obtaines a more certaine courſe of trade, when by the <hi>Rates</hi> ſet and taxed hee knowes certainly what his forreine Species will yeeld him inſtantly vpon his arriuall without delay or diffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cultie. And ſince for theſe intents the <hi>Exchanger</hi> main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines ſtocke-ſeruants and other incident charges, <hi>Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus eſt over arius mercede ſua. Et qui ſentit onus ſentire debet &amp; commodum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Secondly, The taking of the j<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>per</hi> noble is not gran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted (though warranted by jx. <hi>H.</hi> 5. cap. 2. (as j<hi rend="sup">d</hi> ob. <hi>per</hi> noble by 1. <hi>H.</hi> 6. cap 4.) but the exceeding thereof only reſtrayned: And in the Extent or Latitude allowed (of 3<hi rend="sup">d</hi> 
                  <hi>per</hi> pound exchanged) The Exchanger (ſince the Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porter is free to goe to the Mynt,) muſt guide himſelfe
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:17603:18"/>and driue his Exchanges vpon ſuch reaſonable rates and prices as may inuite the Merchant vnto him. It being certaine that he will not come to the Exchanger but go to the Mynt: vnleſſe his benefit and accommodation by the Exchange be made anſwerable to the price he giues for the ſame.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, His late Maieſtie hauing abated his Coyne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nage of gold by proclamation 4. <hi>May x<hi rend="sup">mo</hi>
                  </hi> publiſhed a valuation of forreine Coine and <hi>Bullion.</hi> And this was made by the aduice and with the godd conſent of Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chants called therevnto. And according as the ſame Species were by the ſaid Merchants accepted of abroad, Intending as is likewiſe expreſſed in the ſame Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation, that theſe prices would inuite the Merchants to bring in great ſtore of forreine Coyne and Bullion to the Mynt. With expreſſe prohibition, that none ſhould exceede theſe rates. The office notwithſtanding giues greater rates for euery ounce of Crowne gold or of 22. <hi>Carotts fine,</hi> which is there ſet at 3<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. the Ounce, There is giuen for it in Ingot at the Office 3<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. 8<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. the Ounce. And in ſpecies 3<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. 6<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. For Angels, and Spurrials in ſpecies 3<hi rend="sup">l</hi>. 12<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. the ounce <hi>though theſe are one quarter of a graine worſe then Standard:</hi> And ſo the office gets not ij<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. <hi>per</hi> xx<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. exchanged. And ſtay often a moneth for the returne. And ſince that Proclamation, ſeconded by that of the 5<hi rend="sup">th</hi> February 16. <hi>Iacobi,</hi> There hath bin no cauſe by alteration of the monyes, why the prices well liked of then ſhould not pleaſe now. And it is moſt vntrue that the Goldſmiths doe conſtantly exchange for 2<hi rend="sup">ſ</hi>. <hi>per</hi> pound weight of gold. For that could not returne him the vſe of the ſtocke: And he muſt needes
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:17603:18"/>then be a looſe by his trade: When hee doth ſoe, hee makes vſe of the Merchants ſtocke, and payes him on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with his owne at the deliuery our of the Tower: But the Goldſmiths rates are, according to the skilfulnes or neceſſity of the ſeller, vpon which he will be ſure to make his aduantage, to ſarr greater profit. And as to the loſſe ſuppoſed to the people in generall of x. s. <hi>per</hi> pound of Gold. It will eaſily bee maintayned, that the ſubiect in generall, recemes more at the Office, then from the Goldſmiths; beſices that, neyther his ignorance nor wants can there be wrought vpon: but ſhall certainly and at firſt there receiue the full value of his Coyne or <hi>Bullion.</hi> Which thing how advantagious it is to the ſimple or neceſſitous, may eaſily be apprehended.</p>
               <p>And to the 6. <hi>Article;</hi> Implying matter of danger to be raiſed to the Importer by diſcovery from the Office. Though it bee grounded vpon a falſe ſuppofall, that hee is conſtrained to carry his <hi>Bullicn</hi> into one mans hand, whereas he is free to carry the ſame to the Mynt at his Election: Yet for further anſwere, <hi>It is plaine:</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. The Merchant is more ſecured by a ſworne <hi>Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice</hi> then by any <hi>Goldſmiths</hi> Servant who manageth the buſineſſe for his Maſter. And the diſcoverie thence is more eaſie as the Diſcouerers more, of leſſe truſt and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilitie and not ſo readily found out; Nor can this bee preſumed ſince no Experience ſhewes, that euer from his Maieſties miniſters when they executed this Office any danger arriued, though at thoſe times Penalties
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:17603:19"/>from forreine parts for Exportation were as ſevere and ſtrict as at this preſent.</p>
               <p n="2">2. No man can ſay, that a Merchant or his Factor bringing <hi>Species</hi> to the Exchanger was the <hi>Importer;</hi> ſince heere they may vſe one anothers name &amp; ſervants: No more then it cna be concluded, That pieces of viij. <hi>Reals,</hi> or <hi>French Crownes,</hi> or <hi>Fiſtolets</hi> imported, came from <hi>Spaine</hi> or <hi>France,</hi> ſince theſe may and doe come from diuers other parts where theſe <hi>Species</hi> are Currant, and traded as Merchandize, as in <hi>Holland,</hi> divers parts of <hi>Italie</hi> and elſewhere.</p>
               <p n="3">3. No Regiſter is to bee kept of the name of the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon</hi> to the danger of the Merchant: but of the <hi>thing onely</hi> for the ſecuritie of his Maieſtie, to charge the <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changer</hi> to carry the ſame to his Maieſties mynt for in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Coyne.</p>
               <p>The iſſue of all which precedent Diſcoure is: That ſince <hi>the Exchange of Bullion</hi> is now cleerely <hi>his Maieſties Right,</hi> and <hi>no part of the Goldſmiths trade:</hi> And that the due Exerciſe thereof cannot bee but with <hi>good likelyhood of advantages to the King and Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth;</hi> aſwell by <hi>preventing</hi> the Abuſes and Errors aboue-mentioned, as by <hi>obtayning thoſe</hi> benefits a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boue likewiſe in part intimated; That the true State of the queſtion betwixt his Maieſtie and the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths is, <hi>Not</hi> that there ſhould bee ſhowne of his Maieſties behalfe, eyther reaſons to mooue his Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumption, or declarations to perſwade the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies therefo; for his Ma<hi rend="sup">tie</hi> hauing in Law alwayes bin in poſſeſſion thereof And now being ſo <hi>de facto,</hi>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:17603:19"/>It reſts vpon the part of ſuch as Petition for his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſties laying downe, this auncient Right and Flowre of the Crowne; To propound, ſome moſt juſt eui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent and neceſſary reaſons and motiues, vpon which his Maieſtie ſhould bee moued to remit and quite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime eyther to the Goldſmiths in particular, or o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſubiects in generall this ſo <hi>Royall</hi> and <hi>legall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatiue.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Vpon conſideration whereof (being humbly preſented to his Maieſty) ſuch reſolution no queſtion will be taken as ſhall beſt ſtand with his Maieſties Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and the good of his <hi>Realmes.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. 4.</hi> The proceedings and debatements had in bringing the ſame to Reſolution.</head>
               <p>THe Propoſition for Reviuing the Office of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>change, was preſented to the Earle of <hi>Holland</hi> about the beginning of Summer, 1626. And a Reference was made to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. Attorney and others, who reported the Legalitie, and that it was his Maieſties Right, leauing the point of Conueniencie. About Chriſtmas after, the firſt Letters Patents and Indenture were paſſed, and a Proclamation according to the vſuall forme of ſuch like graunts was to follow. The Lord Treaſurer was ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with the Proclamation, Letters Patents and Indenture; who thereupon ordered the Officers of the Mynt ſhould attend him therein. And they then deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:17603:20"/>in ſome exceptions to the ſame, partly clayming the place to bee in graunt to the Warden of the Mynt, partly vrging inconveniencies, which becauſe they were the ſame with the firſt, 4.5. and ſixt <hi>Article</hi> of the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths Petition aboue recited, are heere omitted. Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtay of the buſineſſe heere, the Goldſmiths ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tayned the Citie to joyne with them in Petitioning the Counſell Table againſt the Office.</p>
               <p>The Earle of <hi>Holland</hi> anſwered this generall Petiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, praying that the Goldſmiths might in particular ſet downe their grieuances, and the inconveniences, whereunto a certaine Anſwer might bee made; And whereupon a certaine iſſue might bee taken to preſerue the buſineſſe from confuſion in the hearing, which be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Ordered, the Goldſmiths herevpon exhibited to their Lordſhips, another Petition declaring at large all their Reaſons againſt the Patent, as well in reſpect of their pretence and clayme to the ſame; as alſo, what preiudice did thereby acrue to their Company in parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; And likewiſe, how inconvenient the ſame was to the Realme. To which his Lordſhip anſwered a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine; and ſo the Cauſe came to a hearing before his Maieſtie and ſome ſixe and twenty Lords and others of his Priuie Counſell, vpon Wedneſday 25. <hi>Aprill,</hi> 1627. and receiued Determination according to the Order hereafter following conceiued vpon the ſame.</p>
               <floatingText xml:lang="eng" type="order">
                  <body>
                     <opener>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Wedneſday the</hi> 25. Aprill, 1627.</date>
                     </opener>
                     <p>THis day the Kings Majeſty being preſent in Counſell,<note place="margin">Order of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell.</note> the reaſons preſented by the Petitioners of the Citie, and of the Goldſwiths; as likewiſe, ſuch other Exceptions as by diver,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:17603:20"/>Marchants and others, then preſent in perſen and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> Counſell learned, were made againſt the Office of <hi>Exchange</hi> and the Patent Indenture and Proclamation, for the Regula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and the better Execution thereof were taken into Debate and Cor ſideration. And vpon full hearing of all the ſaid par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties and their Counſell at large, and particular Debate of all the Reaſons in the ſaid Petitions alledged, and others then made, it appeared plainly to his Maieſtie and the Board; <hi>That no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing was innovated but the right of an ancient Office, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viued;</hi> And reguſated by the ſaid Jndenture and Procla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation.</p>
                     <p>Neuertheleſſe his Maieſtie gratiouſly inclining to giue com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort to the Goldſmiths, in any thing properly belonging to their trade, and to free the Merchant from any inconuenience or loſſe that might ariſe by the Patent, was pleaſed, and by the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſe of his Councell did ordaine theſe things following to be thus explained and declared.</p>
                     <p>Firſt, that they of the myſtery of the Goldſmiths haue free li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty to buy any plate, or gold and ſiluer, which in the vſe of their trade or myſtery they conuerted into made wares, or other works of, Goldmithry as fully and amply as heretofore they might or could doe, but not to by any manner of gold or ſiluer to fell againe, or to ſerue to the Mynt, or which now are or haue beene, or which hereafter ſhall be his Maieſties Coynes of Gold or Sil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner.</p>
                     <p>Secondly, that all plate wrought, where the faſhion is valuable ſhould be left free to be bought ſold or pawned, by or to any perſons whatſoeuer.</p>
                     <p>Thirdly, that euery one of his Maieſties louing ſubiects ſhould be at liberty to carry their Bullien to the Mint, without being inforced to goe to his Maieſties Exchanges, But none are <hi>to buy Bullion Merchantwiſe, thereof to make profit by carrying the ſame to his Maieſties Mynt,</hi> there to be coined in <hi>damage</hi> or <hi>defraud</hi> of his Maieſties Exchange.</p>
                     <p>Fourthly, where it was alledged, that the Penie in the Noble
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:17603:21"/>to be paid to the Exchanger, might occaſion the higher rates of Bullion and Species, and ſo hinder the Importatin thereof: It is declared that the Penny in the Noble is not ſet as a rate certaine, which the Exchanger is to take, but ſuch onely which the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>changer is not to exceede, but may take leſſe as the Exchanger and ſeller ſhall agree, which if they cannot, the ſeller is at liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie to goe to the Mynt, where nothing is to be taken but for the coynage of the ſaid Bullion.</p>
                     <p>Theſe explanations are to bee made in the Proclamation to be publiſhed for he execution of the ſaid Office, and new Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Patents are to paſſe, omitting the graunt of any part of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feitures of penall Lawes and Clauſes of Aſſiſtaxce touching the ſame.</p>
                  </body>
               </floatingText>
               <p>
                  <hi>According to this Order the Proclamation was pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed 25.</hi> May, <hi>next enſuing, And the Office was opened the 25. of</hi> Iune <hi>next after. And yet the Goldſmiths</hi> (notwithſtanding all their reaſons were particularly heard ſtated &amp; debated before his Maieſtie and the Board: And after againe, read oner point by point, And they and their Councell were heard to whatſoeuer that they could ſay) <hi>did (the ſame Progreſſe) againe petition his Maieſtie herein, which by his Maieſtie being referred to the end of his Progreſſe, They for that time purſued the ſame no further, but ſince the ſommons of Parliament did againe petition his Maieſtie vpon the former pretentions and allegations, to which his Maieſtie was moſt gracionſly pleaſed to giue this fauourable anſwere.</hi>
               </p>
               <div type="petition">
                  <pb n="33" facs="tcp:17603:21"/>
                  <head>To the Kings moſt Excellent <hi>Maieſtie.</hi> The humble Petition of the Company of Goldſmiths.</head>
                  <p>MOſt humbly ſhewing,<note place="margin">Petition of the Gold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſmiths.</note> That whereas your Maieſtie hath beene lately pleaſed to grant a Patent for your Maieſties ſole Exchanger of Gold and ſilue <hi>Bulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> within your Highnes Dominions, which Office ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing beene long out of vſe and aboſhlied, and now put in practiſe, appeares to bee very inconuenient and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudiciall, not onely to your Maieſtie and the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, and in more particular to your ſubiects, for that it tends to the vtter ſubuerſion and deſtruction of the Company of Goldſmiths, conſiſting of at leaſt 900. families of thouſand of your Highnes people, for although your Maieſtie was graciouſly pleaſed by your Proclamation to declare, that it was not your Highnes meaning to take from your Suppliants any thing that of right belongeth vnto them in their lawfull trades, yet they be reſtrained from buying and carrying any <hi>Bulloin</hi> at all to his Maieſties Mynt, when all other your Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects and ſtrangers are left at liberty, it hauing bin the practiſe of all ages, to inuite all to come to the Mint, yet now the Goldſmiths are accepted and forbidden to buy any <hi>Bullion</hi> except it be old Plate, or ſuch as is manu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>facture alreadie to make plate of, which is the ſtanding of the Kingdome: So that they be depriued of their maintainance and liuelyhood by the ſaid Office; And yet the ſeruice of your Maieſtie and the common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:17603:22"/>vnder pretext whereof this Office was obtained, is no way advanced, but contrariwiſe much hindered and impaired thereby, And whereas it was pretended, that it ſhould be a reformation of abuſes by reſtraint of Tranſportation, it is plaine it rather incourages and make more Tranſporters then haue beene, And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore becauſe it is a great detriment to your Maieſties profit in the Mynt, and to the whole Land being a hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance to the bringing of treaſure into the Kingdome, both which may bee very plainely made to appeare by diuers reaſons.</p>
                  <p>Your Suppliants moſt humbly beſeeches, you wilbe pleaſed to take into conſideration their grieuances, and to compaſſionate them that they may haue the freedome of their trades formerly they haue vſed, that they may be enabled to doe your Maieſtie ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, as heretofore they haue done, which they haue expreſſed by their readineſſe in all obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence to your Maieſtie vpon all occaſions, And your ſupplyants according to their bounden dutie ſhall pray for your Maieſties moſt proſperous Raigne in this world, and eternall happineſſe in the world to come.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="order">
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:17603:22"/>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>White-hall. <date>March, <hi>1627.</hi>
                        </date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Foraſmuch as this Petition of the Company of Goldſmiths containeth the ſame matter in effect which was heretofore taken into conſideration and debated before his Maieſtie and the Lords (with Counſell on both ſides) and finally Ordered and that their right is reſerued vnto them by the ſaid Proclamation, And that contrary to their ſuggeſtion they haue as great libertie (by his Maieſties meere grace and fauour) to goe to his Mynt, as any other his Subiects haue, but not to make a trade and gatne betwixt any other his Mateſties ſubiects and the Mynt, contrary to the policy of all ages, And if they are hindered or reſtrained in any thing belonging of right to their Trades (without vſurpation vpon his Maieſties Regalties) they are free to vſe the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of his Maieſties Lawes for reliefe therein, his Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie willeth that the Petitioners trouble him no further herein without particular matter of wrong, or new grieuance done vnto them by the Execution of the ſaid Patent, whereupon his Maieſtie will take ſuch further conſideration as bee fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
